<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pubs-rsses on Webpage of the Resendis Lab</title>
    <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pubs-rsses on Webpage of the Resendis Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of Centrality Measurements for the Detection of Essential Proteins in Biological Networks.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM27616995/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM27616995/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The space of enzyme regulation in HeLa cells can be inferred from its intracellular metabolome.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM27335086/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM27335086/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the transition from a healthy state to a cancerous one, cells alter their metabolism to increase proliferation. The underlying metabolic alterations may be caused by a variety of different regulatory events on the transcriptional or post-transcriptional level whose identification contributes to the rational design of therapeutic targets. We present a mechanistic strategy capable of inferring enzymatic regulation from intracellular metabolome measurements that is independent of the actual mechanism of regulation. Here, enzyme activities are expressed by the space of all feasible kinetic constants (k-cone) such that the alteration between two phenotypes is given by their corresponding kinetic spaces. Deriving an expression for the transformation of the healthy to the cancer k-cone we identified putative regulated enzymes between the HeLa and HaCaT cell lines. We show that only a few enzymatic activities change between those two cell lines and that this regulation does not depend on gene transcription but is instead post-transcriptional. Here, we identify phosphofructokinase as the major driver of proliferation in HeLa cells and suggest an optional regulatory program, associated with oxidative stress, that affects the activity of the pentose phosphate pathway.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling metabolism: a window toward a comprehensive interpretation of networks in cancer.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM24747697/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM24747697/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Given the multi-factorial nature of cancer, uncovering its metabolic alterations and evaluating their implications is a major challenge in biomedical sciences that will help in the optimal design of personalized treatments. The advance of high-throughput technologies opens an invaluable opportunity to monitor the activity at diverse biological levels and elucidate how cancer originates, evolves and responds under drug treatments. To this end, researchers are confronted with two fundamental questions: how to interpret high-throughput data and how this information can contribute to the development of personalized treatment in patients. A variety of schemes in systems biology have been suggested to characterize the phenotypic states associated with cancer by utilizing computational modeling and high-throughput data. These theoretical schemes are distinguished by the level of complexity of the biological mechanisms that they represent and by the computational approaches used to simulate them. Notably, these theoretical approaches have provided a proper framework to explore some distinctive metabolic mechanisms observed in cancer cells such as the Warburg effect. In this review, we focus on presenting a general view of some of these approaches whose application and integration will be crucial in the transition from local to global conclusions in cancer studies. We are convinced that multidisciplinary approaches are required to construct the bases of an integrative and personalized medicine, which has been and remains a fundamental task in the medicine of this century.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systems biology of cancer: moving toward the integrative study of the metabolic alterations in cancer cells.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM23316163/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM23316163/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the main objectives in systems biology is to understand the biological mechanisms that give rise to the phenotype of a microorganism by using high-throughput technologies (HTs) and genome-scale mathematical modeling. The computational modeling of genome-scale metabolic reconstructions is one systemic and quantitative strategy for characterizing the metabolic phenotype associated with human diseases and potentially for designing drugs with optimal clinical effects. The purpose of this short review is to describe how computational modeling, including the specific case of constraint-based modeling, can be used to explore, characterize, and predict the metabolic capacities that distinguish the metabolic phenotype of cancer cell lines. As we show herein, this computational framework is far from a pure theoretical description, and to ensure proper biological interpretation, it is necessary to integrate high-throughput data and generate predictions for later experimental assessment. Hence, genome-scale modeling serves as a platform for the following: (1) the integration of data from HTs, (2) the assessment of how metabolic activity is related to phenotype in cancer cell lines, and (3) the design of new experiments to evaluate the outcomes of the in silico analysis. By combining the functions described above, we show that computational modeling is a useful methodology to construct an integrative, systemic, and quantitative scheme for understanding the metabolic profiles of cancer cell lines, a first step to determine the metabolic mechanism by which cancer cells maintain and support their malignant phenotype in human tissues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional modules, structural topology, and optimal activity in metabolic networks.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM23071431/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM23071431/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Modular organization in biological networks has been suggested as a natural mechanism by which a cell coordinates its metabolic strategies for evolving and responding to environmental perturbations. To understand how this occurs, there is a need for developing computational schemes that contribute to integration of genomic-scale information and assist investigators in formulating biological hypotheses in a quantitative and systematic fashion. In this work, we combined metabolome data and constraint-based modeling to elucidate the relationships among structural modules, functional organization, and the optimal metabolic phenotype of Rhizobium etli, a bacterium that fixes nitrogen in symbiosis with Phaseolus vulgaris. To experimentally characterize the metabolic phenotype of this microorganism, we obtained the metabolic profile of 220 metabolites at two physiological stages: under free-living conditions, and during nitrogen fixation with P. vulgaris. By integrating these data into a constraint-based model, we built a refined computational platform with the capability to survey the metabolic activity underlying nitrogen fixation in R. etli. Topological analysis of the metabolic reconstruction led us to identify modular structures with functional activities. Consistent with modular activity in metabolism, we found that most of the metabolites experimentally detected in each module simultaneously increased their relative abundances during nitrogen fixation. In this work, we explore the relationships among topology, biological function, and optimal activity in the metabolism of R. etli through an integrative analysis based on modeling and metabolome data. Our findings suggest that the metabolic activity during nitrogen fixation is supported by interacting structural modules that correlate with three functional classifications: nucleic acids, peptides, and lipids. More fundamentally, we supply evidence that such modular organization during functional nitrogen fixation is a robust property under different environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Systems biology of bacterial nitrogen fixation: high-throughput technology and its integrative description with constraint-based modeling.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM21801415/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM21801415/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bacterial nitrogen fixation is the biological process by which atmospheric nitrogen is uptaken by bacteroids located in plant root nodules and converted into ammonium through the enzymatic activity of nitrogenase. In practice, this biological process serves as a natural form of fertilization and its optimization has significant implications in sustainable agricultural programs. Currently, the advent of high-throughput technology supplies with valuable data that contribute to understanding the metabolic activity during bacterial nitrogen fixation. This undertaking is not trivial, and the development of computational methods useful in accomplishing an integrative, descriptive and predictive framework is a crucial issue to decoding the principles that regulated the metabolic activity of this biological process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proteomic patterns of cervical cancer cell lines, a network perspective.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM21696634/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM21696634/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cervical cancer is a major mortality factor in the female population. This neoplastic is an excellent model for studying the mechanisms involved in cancer maintenance, because the Human Papilloma Virus (HPV) is the etiology factor in most cases. With the purpose of characterizing the effects of malignant transformation in cellular activity, proteomic studies constitute a reliable way to monitor the biological alterations induced by this disease. In this contextual scheme, a systemic description that enables the identification of the common events between cell lines of different origins, is required to distinguish the essence of carcinogenesis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling core metabolism in cancer cells: surveying the topology underlying the Warburg effect.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM20811631/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM20811631/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alterations on glucose consumption and biosynthetic activity of amino acids, lipids and nucleotides are metabolic changes for sustaining cell proliferation in cancer cells. Irrevocable evidence of this fact is the Warburg effect which establishes that cancer cells prefers glycolysis over oxidative phosphorylation to generate ATP. Regulatory action over metabolic enzymes has opened a new window for designing more effective anti-cancer treatments. This enterprise is not trivial and the development of computational models that contribute to identifying potential enzymes for breaking the robustness of cancer cells is a priority.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filling kinetic gaps: dynamic modeling of metabolism where detailed kinetic information is lacking.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM19305506/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM19305506/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Integrative analysis between dynamical modeling of metabolic networks and data obtained from high throughput technology represents a worthy effort toward a holistic understanding of the link among phenotype and dynamical response. Even though the theoretical foundation for modeling metabolic network has been extensively treated elsewhere, the lack of kinetic information has limited the analysis in most of the cases. To overcome this constraint, we present and illustrate a new statistical approach that has two purposes: integrate high throughput data and survey the general dynamical mechanisms emerging for a slightly perturbed metabolic network.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulation by transcription factors in bacteria: beyond description.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM19076632/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM19076632/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transcription is an essential step in gene expression and its understanding has been one of the major interests in molecular and cellular biology. By precisely tuning gene expression, transcriptional regulation determines the molecular machinery for developmental plasticity, homeostasis and adaptation. In this review, we transmit the main ideas or concepts behind regulation by transcription factors and give just enough examples to sustain these main ideas, thus avoiding a classical ennumeration of facts. We review recent concepts and developments: cis elements and trans regulatory factors, chromosome organization and structure, transcriptional regulatory networks (TRNs) and transcriptomics. We also summarize new important discoveries that will probably affect the direction of research in gene regulation: epigenetics and stochasticity in transcriptional regulation, synthetic circuits and plasticity and evolution of TRNs. Many of the new discoveries in gene regulation are not extensively tested with wetlab approaches. Consequently, we review this broad area in Inference of TRNs and Dynamical Models of TRNs. Finally, we have stepped backwards to trace the origins of these modern concepts, synthesizing their history in a timeline schema.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metabolic reconstruction and modeling of nitrogen fixation in Rhizobium etli.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM17922569/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM17922569/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Rhizobiaceas are bacteria that fix nitrogen during symbiosis with plants. This symbiotic relationship is crucial for the nitrogen cycle, and understanding symbiotic mechanisms is a scientific challenge with direct applications in agronomy and plant development. Rhizobium etli is a bacteria which provides legumes with ammonia (among other chemical compounds), thereby stimulating plant growth. A genome-scale approach, integrating the biochemical information available for R. etli, constitutes an important step toward understanding the symbiotic relationship and its possible improvement. In this work we present a genome-scale metabolic reconstruction (iOR363) for R. etli CFN42, which includes 387 metabolic and transport reactions across 26 metabolic pathways. This model was used to analyze the physiological capabilities of R. etli during stages of nitrogen fixation. To study the physiological capacities in silico, an objective function was formulated to simulate symbiotic nitrogen fixation. Flux balance analysis (FBA) was performed, and the predicted active metabolic pathways agreed qualitatively with experimental observations. In addition, predictions for the effects of gene deletions during nitrogen fixation in Rhizobia in silico also agreed with reported experimental data. Overall, we present some evidence supporting that FBA of the reconstructed metabolic network for R. etli provides results that are in agreement with physiological observations. Thus, as for other organisms, the reconstructed genome-scale metabolic network provides an important framework which allows us to compare model predictions with experimental measurements and eventually generate hypotheses on ways to improve nitrogen fixation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modular analysis of the transcriptional regulatory network of E. coli.</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM15680508/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/pubs/PM15680508/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The transcriptional network of Escherichia coli is currently the best-understood regulatory network of a single cell. Motivated by statistical evidence, suggesting a hierarchical modular architecture in this network, we identified eight modules with well-defined physiological functions. These modules were identified by a clustering approach, using the shortest path to trace regulatory relationships across genes in the network. We report the type (feed forward and bifan) and distribution of motifs between and within modules. Feed-forward motifs tend to be embedded within modules, whereas bi-fan motifs tend to link modules, supporting the notion of a hierarchical network with defined functional modules.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>