<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Softwares on Webpage of the Resendis Lab</title><link>https://resendislab.github.io/software/</link><description>Recent content in Softwares on Webpage of the Resendis Lab</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://resendislab.github.io/software/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>micom</title><link>https://resendislab.github.io/software/micom/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://resendislab.github.io/software/micom/</guid><description>micom is a Python package for metabolic modeling of microbial communities developed in the Human Systems Biology Group of Prof. Osbaldo Resendis Antonio at the National Institute of Genomic Medicine Mexico.
micom allows you to construct a community model from a list on input COBRA models and manages exchange fluxes between individuals and individuals with the environment. It explicitly accounts for different abundances of individuals in the community and can thus incorporate data from 16S rRNA sequencing experiments.</description></item><item><title>Our microbiome pipeline</title><link>https://resendislab.github.io/software/microbiome/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://resendislab.github.io/software/microbiome/</guid><description>This repository contains the standardized analysis pipeline for 16S and metagenome data. It serves as a testing ground for what will be required to analyze around 500 samples.</description></item><item><title>CORDA for Python</title><link>https://resendislab.github.io/software/corda/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://resendislab.github.io/software/corda/</guid><description>This is a Python implementation based on the papers of Schultz et. al. with some added optimizations. It is based on the publications of Schultz et. al. [1, 2].
CORDA, short for Cost Optimization Reaction Dependency Assessment is a method for the reconstruction of metabolic networks from a given reference model (a database of all known reactions) and a confidence mapping for reactions. It allows you to reconstruct metabolic models for tissues, patients or specific experimental conditions from a set of transcription or proteome measurements.</description></item><item><title>dycone</title><link>https://resendislab.github.io/software/dycone/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://resendislab.github.io/software/dycone/</guid><description>Dycone (&amp;ldquo;dynamic cone&amp;rdquo;) allows you infer enzymatic regulation from metabolome measurements. It employs formalisms based on flux and k-cone analysis to connect metabolome data to distinct regulations of enzyme activity. Most of the analysis methods can be applied to genome-scale data.</description></item></channel></rss>