<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects-rsses on Webpage of the Resendis Lab</title>
    <link>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects-rsses on Webpage of the Resendis Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://resendislab.github.io/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>In silico study of metabolic reprogramming during epithelial-mesenchymal transition</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/emt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/emt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) is a biologic process that allows a polarized epithelial cell, which normally interacts with basement membrane via its basal surface, to undergo multiple biochemical changes that enable it to assume a mesenchymal cell phenotype, which includes enhanced migratory capacity, invasiveness, elevated resistance to apoptosis, and greatly increased production of ECM components. EMT induces invasive properties in epithelial tumors and promotes metastasis. Although EMT-mediated cellular and molecular changes are well understood, very little is known about EMT-induced metabolic changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project combine high-throughput data to understand metabolic changes before and after EMT in lung cancer cell lines. In particular to find main fluxes used during EMT.  To that extent we employ methods from bioinformatics and Systems Biology. Our goal is to found specific targets which could stop  or reverse EMT in cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating transcriptomic and metabolomic to understand hepatocellular carcinoma in a rat model</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/hepato/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/hepato/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is now the third leading cause of cancer deaths worldwide, with over 500,000 people affected. It occurs predominantly in patients with underlying chronic liver disease and cirrhosis. Despite this, knowledge about the metabolic states of this disease is limited.
Using a rat model that recreates some of the most important characteristics of HCC, including cirrhosis, we aim to understand the metabolic state when compared to healthy liver. To this end we will integrate transcriptomic and metabolic data in a systems biology framework that point us changes in reactions.
This data would not only helped us identify reactions important to maintain the cancerous state but also help us survey the regulatory mechanism this is achieved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metabolic heterogeneity in cancer and its applications in Personalized Medicine</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/prolif/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/prolif/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cancer is a very heterogeneous disease and tumors can differ greatly across and within different cancer types. Consequently, cancer is not a single disease but thousands. One property shared by all cancers is the ability to sustain chronic uncontrolled proliferation which raises the question how different cancers alter their metabolism in order to achieve consistent proliferation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project we combine large-scale genomic data from DNA and RNA sequencing as well as proteomics and metabolomics to understand the connection between variations in the genotype and cancer metabolism. In particular we are asking the question whether distinct genomic aberrations such as mutations or changes in transcription can be related to respective changes in cellular metabolism. To that extent we employ methods from Systems Biology as well as from Data Science and Machine Learning in order to connect genetic information to specific metabolic phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our aim is to use the knowledge we gain in the context of personalized medicine, particularly the use of genotyping for the prediction of the best course of treatment for a specific patient.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of the microRNAs in the metabolic reprogramming of the MCF-7 cells during the spheroids development</title>
      <link>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/spheroids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://resendislab.github.io/projects/spheroids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alterations in the metabolism are a common property in cancer cells, so that, many efforts have been directed to develop models to understand the mechanism by which cancer cells behave differently compared to normal tissues. In recent years, it has been reported that microRNAs (miRNAs) are involved in the regulation of all biological process, and there are evidences that shown its dysregulation play an important role in the development and progression of cancer. Hence, generate models that allow the integration of  miRNAs regulation in cancer metabolism will allow us to analyze in a systematically and systemic manner the relations and potential mechanism underlying between miRNAs and central pathways of metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is imperative to know the mechanism governing the pathogenesis and progression of cancer to design therapies with greater impact on diagnosis and disease progression. So, this project aims to suggest mechanism that trigger the metabolic change in a breast cancer cell line (MCF-7), integrating miRNAs network. To this end, we propose to develop a scheme of systems biology, which allow us to make an integrative analysis of regulatory networks of miRNAs and metabolism in MCF-7. This approach will allow us to develop models capable of identifying potential therapeutic targets with greater impact, biomarkers that allow early detection of cancer and penetrate in global mechanism in clinical cases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>